hey what's up guys my name is Jonah
welcome back to my state plus plus
series so today we're gonna be talking
all about function pointers in C++ and
specifically we're gonna be talking
about the kind of raw style function
pointers that really come from C so
don't think that I'm kind of being
misleading or anything like that we are
going to get into more this C++ way to
do function pointers in a later video
along with things like lambdas which are
anonymous functions kind of without a
formal function definition and all that
stuff we'll get into that as we go along
but first I want to start off with kind
of the most primitive thing which is
kind of what I like to call a raw
function pointer which again comes from
safe so what is a function pointer so
we've learned about pointers if you guys
haven't seen that video it's linked up
there make sure you understand what
pointers are you don't necessarily need
to understand how memory works or how
pointers working in C++ to kind of use
function pointers but you definitely do
need to watch that video so definitely
check it out
but basically function pointers are just
a way to assign a function to a variable
so functions usually as we've been using
them now if you don't know what a
function is by the way I did make a
video on that a while back so definitely
check that out as well but the way that
we've kind of been using functions so
far has just been like as something that
we call right it's not it we can't
really like do any sort of logic with
functions it's just like a symbol that
we can call when we want something to
happen and we can of course give it
parameters and in turn receive something
in return if we write a function that
returns something out and void so that's
how we've been using functions so far
however you can actually assign
functions to variables and like to
extend from that you can also pass
functions into other functions as
parameters and there's a whole bunch of
things that you can actually do with
functions that really creates for some
interesting and complex logic that would
otherwise be extremely messy to do it
really cleans all of a stuff up so the
best way to demonstrate what a function
pointer is and how to use it and what it
can do is obviously by an example so
let's take a look so the first thing I'm
going to do is write a function and this
is gonna be really simple it's gonna be
a void function it's going to be called
hello world and it's just gonna print
hello world we're gonna start
real simple here okay so hello world
there we go
and then what I'm going to do is of
course just call it normally right
that's how functions work we call it
this one doesn't have any parameters so
we don't need to put any parameters in
and if I run my program of course I'm
going to get the text hello world
printing and you can see here that I do
okay great perfect
now let's assign this function to some
kind of variable now we learn about the
auto keyword and the auto keyword is one
of those things that is actually really
useful with things like function
pointers and we'll definitely get into
that in the future as well but let's
just give Auto a shot and see if we can
assign hello world to order some want to
create a variable called function I'm
going to set it equal to hello world now
it's right away you can see this isn't
working because we can't deduce Auto
type because really hello world returns
void and what we're doing here is we're
actually calling the function but if we
get rid of the parentheses right
suddenly we're not actually calling the
function we're actually getting the
function pointer and specifically this
would look like this with an ampersand
so we're kind of getting the memory
address of that function now functions
are of course just CPU instructions and
they're stored some way in our binary
when we actually compile our code in the
future we might actually take a deep
dive into the binary file and see our
actual CPU instructions and how all that
works but for now just imagine that
literally when you compile your code
every single function gets compiled into
CPU instructions and they are somewhere
in our binary in our executable file
right so what we're doing over here with
this ampersand is we're saying hey in
this executable file let's find this
hello world function and let's get the
memory address of those CPU instructions
that's basically what this is right so
what we're doing is we're retrieving the
location of the instructions to execute
when this function gets called and so
now we don't actually have to use this
ampersand by the way because there is an
implicit conversion which we'll see in a
minute so you can just do this right
hello world and that's it so now what I
can do is I can actually call my
function like this and let's actually
call it twice I'll hit f5 and you can
see that I get hollow it well printing
twice so that's pretty cool we've
actually managed to assign a function to
a variable now this is order but what
type is this
actually well if we hover our mouse over
this look at what we get we get void and
then like an asterisk and then function
and some parentheses looks a bit weird
so let's actually write out that type so
we get void then we need to give us some
kind of name in our case because we are
creating a variable so before we called
it function let's call it function again
so in parentheses I'm putting an
asterisk followed by the name of my
variable and then any parameters that my
function might take so if it took an
integer I would put in int like that if
it took a string I would put in string
now we're not taking anything as you can
see this is just no no parameters here
so I can just kind of end it like that
this is the actual type now this does
look weird because this well this is
ultimately the type kind of right it's
just that we need to give it a name like
any other variable and function just
happens to be the name this can be
chanted this can be anything you want
it's just a name and then what we can
kind of do here is just a sign churner
to say hello world or something like
that and you can see that it works like
any other variable and you can of course
do that here as well if I just write
hello world that also works like that
okay it does look very confusing that's
gonna be step one like I've called the
channel
a cold shot over here like as if it was
a function if I hit up five of course it
still works this does look confusing I
totally agree which is why what people
tend to do with function pointers like
this is either use author or my kind of
preferred way is actually to type def at
all using it so we're basically creating
an alias for it so what I mean by that
is instead of this kind of weird code
what we can actually do is say type def
then this actual type here and we can
call it like our I don't know hello
world function or something like that
right and of course this hello world
function name goes into here because
that's our actual name so it's basically
the type but we put a start out at the
front what that now means is that if I
want to actually use this I can just
type in hello world function then a
variable name like function equals hello
world and then of course I can just call
function like that okay let's make this
a little bit more exciting I'm gonna add
a parameter here it's gonna be an
integer is gonna be called
a and then at the end of hello world I'm
actually going to print value and then a
just like that whoops let's put this on
the right side all right so now this
hello well function of course we get an
error here we can't assign it because
hello world is a function that takes in
an integer so what I'm going to do is
change my function definition here to
actually include an integer as a
parameter and now you can see this works
and when we call this function which
we're doing over here we now need to
specify an integer so I'm going to type
in 8 and then hit f5 to run my code and
you can see now I get the value 8
printing so what I've kind of done now
is I have a function that I can call
using a variable name like this and of
course it's parameterised so I can put
anything I wanted to here and it will
call that function with different values
which again is pretty cool so that's the
that's the basics of how it works that
should probably show you enough to use
it in pretty much all of its capacity
but now let's take a look at an actually
useful example of why you might want to
use function pointers in the first place
so suppose that I have a vector and just
include a vector over here
don't delete this code as well and all
of this in fact I have a vector of
integers I'll call this values I'm just
going to cyan't using this kind of
initialize a list here like that okay
and I want to create some kind of
function which iterates through all of
this and perform some kind of action so
of course a for each loop is basically
what I'm writing here but let's pretend
that I wanted it to be in a function
because maybe did some other things as
well and that's just the example so what
I'm going to do is I'm going to write a
for each function I'll pull it for H
it's going to take in this standard
vector of integers called values and
then it's going to do something so I'll
just say for int value in the values and
then we want to actually do something so
let's go ahead and call this Oh H values
now how do we tell this function what we
want it to actually do for each of these
values well the way we're gonna do it is
just by passing in a function
essentially so up here I'm going to
create a function I want to call this
print value it's going to take in a
value and almost going to do is
we print it so value and then the value
very simple function right and so what
I'm going to do here is inside for each
I'm actually going to write one more
parameter here that actually is this
function so it's going to be void the
name I'm going to call is func and then
of course it takes one parameter which
is an integer so I'm going to write in
like that and then inside this for each
loop I'm actually just going to write
func and then call it with value as the
parameter of course because that's the
current iteration of the for loop and
then inside is 4-h I'm passing in the
values of course which is our vector and
I'm also going to pass in this function
which is called print value so now
basically what we've got is a function
into which we can pass in a vector of
integers and for each of these integers
inside this vector it's going to execute
this function that's what's happening
over here and you can see what that
looks like so if I hit f5 you can see
what I get here I get all these integers
that I've got one five four two and
three as I defined with my list here and
I'm getting this print value function
executed with each of these integers as
a parameter so that's pretty cool it's a
way that we can kind of tell our
function hey I want you to do this at a
particular time now this might seem a
little bit overkill so I'll show you one
more way to kind of do this and this
will kind of late into the next video
that we have so instead of kind of
defining this function it's a little bit
messy just have an extra function
floating around especially if we only
intend for it to be used inside this 4-h
function so what we can do is use
something called a lambda and lambda is
essentially a normal function except
it's not declared as a normal function
like this it's kind of just declared
during our code and it's kind of a
throwaway function that isn't actually a
real function it's an anonymous function
and the way that we can kind of declare
that is by using square brackets like
this parenthesis like this will take you
now actual parameter that we need to
take in here which is out value and then
with curly brackets we basically tell it
what we want it to do so as if it was
any other function so we'll save current
value and then the actual value that we
have which is going to be value which is
the parameter that we passed in okay
just like that pretty simple stuff let's
hit f5 and you can see that I get my
values printing like before but we don't
have an X
function we've literally just kind of
written an inline these square brackets
I was called CAPTCHA method so that's
how we pass variables in from the
outside world our parameters going here
and inside and this is just like any
other function body we could even run it
like this if you wanted to and you can
see that's the actual function okay
we're gonna talk way more about lambdas
in a video dedicated to lambdas we're
also going to talk about something
called STD function which is standard
function and standard binds and all that
stuff so there's a lot more to actually
discuss to do with function pointers
this is just kind of a gentle
introduction so that you can see what
they are and how we can use them and all
of that and also the primitive way of
how they exist in C which is just kind
of like this void and then it's just the
the signature is really really weird and
almost no one uses this in actual C++
anymore but definitely be aware of it
because you will see a lot of code like
that just in your programming life
anyway I hope you guys enjoyed this
video if you did you can hit that like
button you can help support this series
by going to patreon.com/scishow Cherno
there are some really cool rewards that
you'll get there for helping to support
this series such as getting videos early
and like monthly kind of hangout
sessions which we do and access to
source code from all my other series and
all that kind of cool stuff thank you
huge thank you as always to all the
patreon supporters this series would not
be here without you so thank you so much
I will see you guys next time goodbye
[Music]